## **Curriculum Vitae**

# **Christopher James Shepherd**

74 Wolverton Road, Leicester, LE3 2AJ chris\_shepherd2@hotmail.com +447929 672636 www.github.com/cshep4/

Full clean driving licence Car owner

### **Profile**

Highly motivated and skilled software development professional with two and a half years' experience in software design, development and integration. Proficient in several programming languages such as Java, C++, PHP, Node.js, HTML, CSS and SQL with knowledge in various agile software development methodologies.

### **Experience**

## October 2015-Present – IBM, Developer:

- Currently working as a back-end developer using Java 8 and Spring Boot with Maven. We use Jenkins for Continuous Integration and SonarQube for code quality analysis. GitLab is used as source control. Our application uses RabbitMQ as a JMS message broker and Redis for cache management.
- I am using various software development techniques such as Test Driven Development and Agile SAFE.
- Prior to my current role, I was a full stack developer writing in Java, using Spring Boot with Gradle and AngularJS to create a mobile app. The project used TDD and pair programming. Jenkins was also used for Continuous Integration and GitHub for version control.
- I also worked on a project taking the role of a Java developer for a large external client in the insurance industry. This was using the Spring MVC framework. This was carried out using the Scrum framework.
- Responsibilities for each project have included developing user stories, fixing defects and code reviewing.
- Carried out a short cognitive side project for a PoC. I created a back-end using Node.js and Express to link a mobile app with IBM's Watson Conversation web service and a Cloudant NoSQL database.
- I have undertaken several training courses, both technical and non-technical, including MEAN Stack, Core Java, Java Spring and an Agile DevOps Workshop.
- I am part of the Blockchain Practice Area, this involves carrying out training and gaining the IBM Blockchain Essentials for Developers certification.
- I have taken and passed the Oracle Certified Java Associate certification and plan to take the next level, Oracle Certified Java Programmer certification within the next quarter.

#### May 2012-September 2012; June 2013-August 2014 – Motor Design Ltd, Software Developer:

Motor Design Ltd is a company that produces Motor-CAD, a thermal analysis software package for electric motors and generators. I carried out an industrial placement year as part of my degree and was subsequently nominated by them for the Placement Student of the Year award.

- Learned and utilised advanced skills programming in Object Pascal using Delphi XE2, creating various features for a software package by interpreting physics and mathematical equations.
- Created conductor placement and magnetic winding design tools for Motor-CAD.
- Produced an interactive editor for solver circuit design also for Motor-CAD.
- Implemented functionality for Motor-CAD to check for updates using a PHP script I created on the company website
- Greatly developed my analytical skills and programming ability, as well as encouraging working using my own initiative.

### **Education**

## <u>De Montfort University, Leicester – First Class BSc Hons, Computer Games Programming:</u>

2014-2015 – Third year modules: Games Programming

Mobile Games Development

Secure Web Application Development

Fuzzy Logic and Knowledge Based Systems (AI)

Final Year Project

2012-2013 – Second year modules: C++ for Games Programmers

Artificial Intelligence and Modelling for Games

Introduction to Graphics and Interactive 3D Modelling

**Database Design and Implementation** 

2011-2012 – First year modules: C++ Programming

Games Architecture, Design and Development

Creative Client Computing

**Computer Systems** 

## Shrewsbury Sixth Form College, Shrewsbury:

2009-2011 – A-Levels: Subject Grade

Computing B
Mathematics B
Physics E

## Lakelands School, Sports and Languages College:

2004-2009 – GCSEs: 9 GCSEs grade A-C, including Mathematics, English and Science.

### **Relevant Projects**

### **University Projects**

- 1. Created various applications using C++ including a 3D game engine from scratch.
- 2. The module I undertook in Artificial Intelligence, involves learning path finding algorithms such as A\* Search, Depth First Search and Breadth First Search and implementing them in C++.
- 3. Studied a Mobile Game Development module, which focused on Android app design and development. I since have created an Android called "Monster Attack". This was written in Java.
- 4. Carried out a module in Secure Web Application Development, where I created a web application with a Model View Controller architecture which uses a M2M web service to send and receive SMS messages, this was produced using BDD and TDD methodologies.
- 5. Developed a Final Year Project for a social media website for students to meet and chat with future flat mates, using HTML, CSS, PHP, JQuery, MySQL and JavaScript.

### Personal projects:

- 1. Developed EURO 2016 and Premier League predictor websites for users to compete against friends by predicting football scores. These are written in HTML/CSS, PHP, MySQL and JavaScript and use RESTful APIs to get the most up to date news and scores. These are written with MVC architectures.
- 2. Developed a gym tracking application where users can log in, store their performance in the gym and view progress with various analytics. Written in HTML/CSS, PHP, MySQL and JavaScript. This is written with an MVC architecture. The website is hosted using IBM cloud services on Bluemix and the MySQL database is hosted using AWS Relational Database Service. IBM Delivery Pipeline is used for Continuous Integration and Delivery, meaning the application is rebuilt and deployed every time a change is committed to GitHub. The website URL is www.gyme.co.uk.
- 3. Currently redeveloping the mobile game I created "Monster Attack" from scratch. This is now written using Java 8 and will be fully unit tested. I plan to release this to the Google Play Store in the near future.